眼K不
Seeing is not believing.
我的感官`我
Our senses can deceive us.
@些星星K不是我看到的幼
Even the stars are not what they appear to be.
通^科W展示出的宇宙
The cosmos, as revealed by science,
比我所能想像的更x奇
is stranger than we ever could have imagined.
光 rg 空g f有引力
Light and time and space and gravity
共同造出
conspire to create realities
我奈大w^的F
which lie beyond human experience.
我一探究竟
That's where we're headed.
跟我
Come with me.
1802年 像@拥囊夜晚
Back in 1802, on a night like this,
天文W家威廉・赫歇和他的鹤
the astronomer William Herschel strolled the beach
在英海散步
on the English coast, with his son John.
赫歇是有史以淼谝晃
Herschel was the first person ever
a星天文W之父
看穿宇宙深W秘的人
to see into the deeper waters of the cosmic ocean.
他看穿了光和rg
There he glimpsed the magic trick
一起出的蚍
that light does with time.
父H
Father...
你相信有鬼魂
do you believe in ghosts?
怎N了  我相信
Why, yes, my son!
你信
You, you do?
我真]想到
I would not have thought so.
不是人死後的鬼魂
Oh, no, not in the human kind of ghost.
^不是那N
No... not at all.
抬^看 鹤
But look up, my boy,
天空中M是鬼魂
and see a sky full of them.
星星  父H
The stars, Father?
我]懂
I do not follow.
每星星都像我的太那N亮 那N大
Every star is a sun as big, as bright as our own.
想想看要把太移到多h以外
Just imagine how far away from us you'd have to move the Sun
才能它看上去像星星那有
to make it appear as small and faint as a star.
星星l出的光 速度很快
The light from the stars travels very fast...
最快的速度
faster than anything...
但K不是o限的快
but not infinitely fast.
星光到_我@Y需要rg
It takes time for their light to reach us.
最近的可能需要啄
For the nearest ones, it takes years.
其他那些  装倌
For others, centuries.
有一些特eh的
Some stars are so far away,
需要|f年才能到_地球
it takes eons for their light to get to Earth.
等那些星星l出的光到_@Y
By the time the light from some stars gets here,
星星已死了
they are already dead.
@些星星碚f  我看到的只是他的鬼魂
For those stars, we see only their ghosts.
我看到他的光
We see their light,
但他的星球已死了很久很久
but their bodies perished long, long ago.
s翰  我比我的古人
John, I have seen further back in time
能看到更古老的^去
than any man before me--
装偃f年前的^去
millions of years into the past.
威廉・赫歇是第一JR到
William Herschel was the first person to understand
望hR就是一rgC器
that a telescope is a time machine.
我看向太空
We cannot look out into space
就是看向^去
without seeing back in time.
一秒  光穿越30f公里
In one second, light travels 300,000 kilometers,
或者18f6千英里
or 186,000 miles.
缀蹙褪堑厍虻皆铝恋木嚯x
That's nearly the distance from the Earth to the Moon.
所以月亮x我1光秒
So, the Moon is about one light-second away.
下次你看向月亮
The next time you look at the Moon,
你就看到1秒以前的^去
you'll be seeing one second into the past.
宇宙大探索
第四集
太
That Sun...
K不真的在那位置
it's not really there.
太H上升出地平
It won't actually be above the horizon
是煞昼以後的事情
for another two minutes.
日出只是幻象
The sunrise is an illusion.
大邮股淙氲年光l生了折射
Earth's atmosphere bends the incoming rays of sunlight
就像R片和一杯水那
like a lens or a glass of water.
所以我看到的只是地平之上的投影
So we see the image of the Sun projected above the horizon...
太本身]到_那位置
before the physical Sun is actually there.
我身後的太只是海市蜃
That Sun behind me is a mirage.
就像那Wq的D像
No more real than the shimmering image
漂浮在
that hovers in the distance
炎崽庀碌纳衬h方
over a desert road on a hot day.
日光需要8分才能_到地球
Sunlight takes about eight minutes to reach Earth,
太x我8光分
so the Sun is eight light-minutes away.
於太碚f  我只能看到它
From Earth, we can only ever see the Sun
8分之前的幼
as it was eight minutes ago.
有一件事
And another thing,
太K不是真的 升起
the Sun doesn't really "rise" at all.
地球е我一起旋D
The Earth turns and we turn with it.
看上去也S不像  但是@r候
It may not look like it, but right at this moment,
我比wC走的快
I'm moving faster than a jet plane
你也是  其他所有人都一
and so are you and everyone on Earth.
我看^去
While I'm at it,
地平
that horizon...
K不真的存在
it's not really there at all.
根本]有
There's no edge.
地平也只是一N幻象
The horizon is just another illusion.
地球x最外的行星
The distance between Earth
海王星的距x
and the outermost planet Neptune
S著h日道而不同
varies as the planets orbit the Sun.
平均碚f  光要4小r才能
On average, the light makes that trip in four hours.
所以ξ碚f
So for us on Earth,
我看到的是4小r前海王星的幼
the Neptune we see is always four hours in the past--
距x 4光r
four light-hours away.
但行星g的距x
But the distances to the planets,
就算最bh的
even the farthest one...
相π窍甸g和a星g的距x碚f
are mere baby steps on a much grander scale
也只不^是微不足道的
of the stars and galaxies.
一旦我x_太系
As soon as we leave the Sun's immediate neighborhood,
我就需要把距x挝
we need to change the unitive distance
墓rQ到光年
from light-hours to light-years.
光年是宇宙中的距x挝
A light-year is the yardstick of the cosmos.
1光年⒔10f|公里
A single one is nearly ten trillion kilometers,
大s6f|英里
or about six trillion miles.
宇宙距x挝恢  就像1米或1英里那
It's a unitive distance, just like a meter or a mile.
它是光用1年rg可以穿越的距xL度
It's the distance light travels in a year.
x太最近的a星  比星
The nearest star to the Sun, Proxima Centauri,
由天文W家_伯特・因尼斯於1915年在南非lF
x地球的距x超^4光年一cc
is a little more than four light-years away from Earth.
4光年有多h
How far away is four light-years?
NASA的旅行者探y器
NASA's Voyager spacecraft moves
速度超^每小r5f6千公里
at more than 56,000 kilometers an hour.
就算@N@人的速度
Even at that astonishing speed, it would take Voyager
也需要超^8f年  才能到_最近的a星
more than 80,000 years to reach the nearest star.
昂宿星F的a星
And the stars of the Pleiades cluster,
一大而明亮的疏散星F，位於金牛座，裸眼就可以p易的看
距x我 400光年
400 light-years away.
想像之舟
The Ship of the Imagination
有著一N不同こ５哪芰
is equipped with a highly unusual capability--
一o二的
one-of-a-kind, actually.
它能我看到
It makes it possible for us to see what was happening
光倪bh的a星或星系l出
when the light from a distant star or galaxy first set out
直到地球的情形
on its long journey to Earth.
400年前  光年乃扌F出lr
When that light left the Pleiades, about 400 years ago,
伽利略第一次使用望hR
Galileo was taking his first look through a telescope.
啄赆 他Ly算光的速度
A few years later, he tried to measure the speed of light,
甲乙扇嗽谝寡Y相隔一段距x面γ嬲局，每人都拿一K提簟
甲首先_簦乙一看到甲的艄饬⒖檀蜷_自己的簟
但是]有成功
but he couldn't do it.
他的很高明  可惜r的科技
He had a very clever plan, but the technology of that era
甲下淖约洪_羝鸬娇吹揭业艄橹顾^的rg。
然後用甲乙之g距x的杀度コ以@rg，就得到光的速度。
不能y量那N快的速度
just wasn't good enough to measure the motion of anything
像光那N快的速度
that moves as fast as light.
我牡厍蛏嫌^察蟹钚请r
When we look at the Crab Nebula from Earth,
我看到的是更古老的^去
we're seeing much farther back in time.
蟹钚请曾是一w巨大的a星
The Crab Nebula was once a giant star,
|量比太大10倍
ten times the mass of the Sun,
爆炸成橐活w超新星
until it exploded in a supernova.
它的中心是w}n星
At its heart is a pulsar,
城市般大小的一w坍塌星
a collapsed star the size of a city,
中子星
每秒自D30次
spinning 30 times a second.
}n星的螺旋磁
This pulsar's whirling magnetic field
狂地 周的子
whips nearby electrons into a frenzy,
⑺加速到接近光的速度
accelerating them to almost the speed of light.
他l出They shine with a blue glow that lights up the tendrils of gas
a生的B贼P
still unraveling from the supernova.
蟹钚请
The Crab Nebula
距x地球大s6500光年
is about 6,500 light-years from Earth.
在某些宗教信仰中
According to some beliefs,
那是整宇宙的年o
that's the age of the whole universe.
但如果宇宙只有6500q
But if the universe were only 6,500 years old,
我怎N可能看到更h的光
how could we see the light from anything more distant
比蟹钚请h的光
than the Crab Nebula?
做不到
We couldn't.
那K]有足虻rg
There wouldn't have been enough time for the light
光木嚯x超^6500光年的地方
to get to Earth from anywhere farther away
淼厍
than 6,500 light-years in any direction.
那crg只蚬庠
That's just enough time for light to travel
我的y河系中穿越很短的距x
through a tiny portion of our Milky Way galaxy.
如果相信宇宙
To believe in a universe
只有6千到7千q
as young as 6,000 or 7,000 years old
就是熄缌算y河系中大部分的光
is to extinguish the light from most of the galaxy,
更e提那些可^y宇宙中
not to mention the light from all the 100 billion
上千|星系l出的光
other galaxies in the observable universe.
我y河系的中心
The center of our own galaxy
距x地球大s3f光年
is about 30,000 light-years from Earth.
我今天看到的光
The light we see today
你y河系的核心出lr
coming from the core of the Milky Way left there...
我的h古祖先找到了
when our ancestors were perfecting a way
超越死亡的方法
to vanquish death...
使用L的力量
by making art with the power
o予後世⑹
to inspire those who would come long after they were gone.
拈帽星系淼墓
The light we see coming from the Sombrero Galaxy
其碛忻髁燎揖薮蟮男窍岛
尤其在赤道方向有一l由星Hm埃所形成的暗
是z影酆谜叩谋囟ㄅzο裰一
走了3千f年
is 30 million years old.
光l出r  我的祖先住在渖
Our ancestors were living in trees when that light started out.
他大s5公斤重  有LL的尾巴
They weighed about five kilos and had long tails.
但就算x我3千f光年之外
But even 30 million light-years away
挠钪嬷锌 也不^就在我的後院
is still in our own cosmic backyard.
那星系凫夺岚l座星系F
That galaxy is part of the Coma Cluster,
3|2千f光年之b
320 million light-years away.
@Y的光出lr
What was going on back home
r的地球又是怎拥哪
when the light you are seeing began its trip to Earth?
]有我熟悉的大  海洋  河流
No familiar continents, oceans or rivers.
我的h古祖先乃中登上地
Our distant ancestors were just leaving the water for the land.
很古老的光
That's pretty old light,
但h不是 我能看到的 最古老的光
but not nearly the oldest light we can see.
最古老的光已很微弱了
The oldest light is very faint,
暗夜中弱的鬼魂
a pale ghost in the night.
看到A圈中的tc
See that red blob inside the circle?
那是我能的最古老星系之一
That's one of the oldest galaxies we've ever seen.
你看到的是134|q高g的星光
You're looking at 13.4-billion year-old starlight
通^哈勃太空望hR捕捉到的
as captured by the Hubble space telescope.
它碜缘谝淮的星星
It's coming from the very first generation of stars.
r的地球什N情r
What was happening on Earth back then?
完全]情r
Absolutely nothing.
r ]有地球 ]有太 ]有y河系
There was no Earth, no Sun, no Milky Way.
它都是资|年後才Q生的
They would not come to be for billions of years.
我看向宇宙的更深
When we try to look even farther into the universe,
好像已到了宇宙的M^
we come to what appears to be the end of space...
但事上
but actually...
@是rg的_始
it's the beginning of time.
地球向下拉著我
Earth pulls on us.
我不嗟胤纯挂力
Our lives are a relentless struggle with gravity.
@小女孩用M全力要爬出
That little girl is trying her best to climb out
引力的包
of a gravitational well.
牡谝淮L站立到最後的倒下
From our first efforts to stand to our final surrender,
我一直在努力克服地心引力
we are struggling to overcome the Earth's pull.
我在重力鲋姓Q生  生活  ^世
We are born, live and die in a force field--
重力缀鹾陀钪姹旧硪拥墓爬
one that is almost as old as the universe itself.
有多古老
And how old is that?
榱讼胂裼钪娴138|年q月
To visualize the 13.8 billion year age of the universe,
我把所有的宇宙rg
we've compressed all of cosmic time
嚎s在一份的年v中
into a single year-at-a-glance calendar.
F在是12月31的午夜
Midnight on December 31 is this very moment right now.
而1月1就是rg的_始
And January 1 is the beginning of time.
看到那耀眼的F
See that glowing fog out there?
它是大爆炸z留下的射物
It's radiation left over from the Big Bang,
在138|年前
the explosion that made the universe
大爆炸造了宇宙
13.8 billion years ago.
F在 我站在已知空g和rg的
Right now, we're at the very edge of known space and time.
那N 大爆炸之前是什N幼幽
So what happened before the Big Bang?
]人知道
Nobody knows.
]有z毫P於那之前的C
No evidence survives from before that moment.
我有一些很狂的猜想
We've got some pretty crazy ideas
是P於宇宙的碓
about where the universe came from,
我以後提到
which we'll get to, in time.
我在宇宙的什N位置
Where are we in the universe?
就在正中心
At the very center.
在已知宇宙中 每人都X得自己很特殊
In the observed universe, everyone gets to feel special.
不你身哪星系
No matter which galaxy you happen to live in,
你看向宇宙r  你lF自己
when you look out to the universe, you'll find yourself
身宇宙地平的中心
at the center of the cosmic horizon.
但@不^是eX
But this is just an illusion.
H上  ]有中心
In reality, there is no center,
宇宙地平和海上的地平 一硬徽
and the cosmic horizon is no more real than the horizon at sea.
@是因 在有起始rg的宇宙中
It's what you get when you have a finite speed of light
光速是有限的
in a universe that had a beginning in time.
大爆炸後的|年
A few hundred million years after the Big Bang,
大量的夂秃怆F
vast clouds of hydrogen and helium condensed
凝Y成最初的a星和星系
into the first stars and galaxies.
有了@些新的光源
With these new sources of light,
宇宙漫L的黑暗r代拇私KY
the long dark ages of the universe ended.
S著宇宙的不嗯蛎
As space continued to expand,
宇宙M化的模得更加宏大
cosmic evolution unfolded on grander scales.
最初的星星死亡
As the first generation of stars died,
他⑤^重的元素散言谟钪嬷
they seeded space with heavier elements,
使得行星的形成 成榭赡
making possible the formation of planets,
最K 生命的形成
and ultimately, life.
大爆炸形成了物|和能量
Matter and energy were formed in the Big Bang.
有
But that's not all.
造了空g和rg
Space and time were created, too,
有束`所有物|的力量
and all the forces that bind matter together,
包括 重力
including gravity.
牛DlF了一W定律
Isaac Newton discovered a mathematical law
可以形容重力的\作C制
that describes how gravity works.
他可以用它解行星g的\
With that law, he could explain the motions of the planets.
100多年後
More than 100 years later,
威廉・赫歇 意R到 那不是全部
William Herschel realized gravity could do much more.
s翰 你能保守秘密
John, can you keep a secret?
可以 父H
Yes, Father.
我有了一lF  ]告V^任何人
I've made a discovery and have yet to tell another soul.
地球上的地心引力
The gravity that holds us to the Earth--
同邮桥ｎDlF的
the same gravity that Newton showed
⑿行潜３衷谲道上的引力
keeps the planets in their orbits--
我lF
I've discovered
也同舆m用於 相隔bh的a星
that it also rules the distant stars.
爹  你咋知道的
Father... but how can you know this?
你能找到Can you find the constellation of the Lion?
在那
There.
值煤
Well done.
你能找到
Can you now find the star
B接^部和身w的那w星
that joins the Lion's head to his body?
那
That one.
那其是深w星
That star is really two stars
靠的很近 看上去就像一w
so close together that they appear to be one.
我用望hR^察了很久
I've been watching them through my telescope
你出生很久前就_始了
since long before you were born.
他非常慢的 @相互移
They dance around each other very slowly.
h比行星@a星\拥穆
More slowly than any planet moves around the Sun.
我今晚看到的S多星星
Many of the stars we see tonight,
可能大部分
perhaps most of them,
按照看不的律移
dance with invisible partners.
f有引力@大帝y治著所有的星球
Gravity's empire governs all the heavens.
1世o前
A century earlier,
艾_克・牛D涫芾_
Isaac Newton had been haunted
他也找不到引力的作用C制
by the same absence of a mechanism for gravity.
相距甚h的物w 如何相互影
How could distant bodies affect each other
不用接|就相互影
across empty space without actually touching?
@他Q之 超距作用 的}困_著他
This "action at a distance," as he called it, baffled him.
19世o ~克・法拉第（W之父）lF
In the 19th century, Michael Faraday discovered
W之父
我被不可的力霭
that we were surrounded by invisible fields of force
@解了引力的\作C制
that explained how gravity works.
O果和地球 K]有l生接|
The apple and the Earth don't touch each other,
但是他之g的力霎a生了接|
but the fields between them do.
他想像引力a生的
He imagined those lines of gravitational force
拿恳物w 向太空中射
radiating out into space from every massive body--
地球 月亮 太  所有的一切
the Earth, the Moon, the Sun, everything.
@就是那困_牛D的}
Here was the answer to that question
的答案
that had stumped Newton.
1985年 詹姆斯・克拉克・克斯f
In 1865, James Clerk Maxwell translated Faraday's idea
把法拉第P於磁龅睦碚
about fields of electricity and magnetism
D化成了W公式
into mathematical laws.
他lF@些磁 龆家圆ǖ男问皆诳臻g中移
He discovered that these fields move through space in waves.
他算它的移铀俣r
When he calculated how fast they move,
Y果是 光的速度
it turned out to be the speed of light.
我才lF了  宇宙@大焯荷系木
We were beginning to discover the threads of the cosmic tapestry,
但是我o法 看出S富的D案
but we were not yet able to discern the rich pattern
rg 光 空g 重力
that time, light, space and gravity weave.
阿伯特・垡蛩固 在柏林
As Albert Einstein worked in Berlin
研究他的引力理r
on his theory of gravity,
上炝诉@3位前的^像
he kept the portraits of these three men before him.
他知道他的成就  建立在他的基A上
He knew he was standing on their shoulders.
多年前  少年r  他有^一D悟
Years before, as a teenager, he had an insight
如同前的理那般@天拥
that was as Earth-shaking as any idea of theirs.
那年夏天
And it happened one summer
他在意大利遐想r的D悟
while he was daydreaming in Italy.
1895年的夏天
In the summer of 1895,
他父H在德的生意失
Einstein's father's business in Germany had failed,
全家搬到了意大利北部
and the family had moved here to northern Italy.
小垡蛩固瓜g在@些路上散步
Young Einstein loved wandering these roads
他的思SS意l散
and giving his mind free rein to explore.
@Y有著某些永a的|西
There's something timeless about this place.
和垡蛩固棺畛醯腻谙r相比
Nothing here has really changed
基本]什N化
since the time of Einstein's early daydreams.
一天 他想到了光
One day, he began to think about light
有光速
and how fast it travels.
日常生活中 我是y量物w
In everyday life, we always measure the speed
相於其他物w的移铀俣
of a moving object with respect to something else.
假O其他物w]有移
Something that's presumably not moving.
宇宙中的其他物w]有\
Something in the cosmos that's not in motion.
比方f  我的速度大s每小r10公里
For example, I'm moving about ten kilometers per hour
相於地面而言
relative to the ground.
但我之前提^  大地也在\
But as I mentioned earlier, the ground is moving.
地球的D速超^每小r1600公里
Earth is turning at more than 1,600 kilometers per hour
在h日道上
while it orbits the Sun
速度超^每小r10f公里
at more than 100,000 kilometers per hour.
K且太系在y河系中\行
And the Sun is moving through the galaxy
s槊啃r90f公里
每小r50f英里的速度
at a half a million miles per hour.
y河系在宇宙中\行
And the Milky Way is moving through the universe
Hs216f公里
速度⒔每小r150f英里
at nearly one and a half million miles an hour.
宇宙中]有不拥牡胤
There is no fixed place in the cosmos.
一切都在\
All of nature is in motion.
π垡蛩固碚f  也是很y想像出
It was hard even for the young Einstein
一^Φ
to imagine some absolute standard
用砗饬克有@些相Φ倪\
to measure all those relative motions against.
就是@本
This is the very book
l了少年垡蛩固
that inspired Einstein as a young boy.
o了他一本  改了@世界
Give a kid a book and you change the world.
某N程度上  改了@宇宙
In a way, even the universe.
看@Y  第一
Look at this-- the very first page,
它描述了令人@的
it describes the astonishing speed
流通^的速度
of electricity through wires
光穿^宇宙的速度
and light through space.
垡蛩固褂得他小r候倪@本YW到的
Einstein remembered what he'd learned as a child from this book
或S 最初 就在@Y
and perhaps, for the first time, right here,
想像著@世界如何
wondered what the world would look like
如果可以用光速\
if you could travel at the speed of light.
垡蛩固乖较
The more Einstein thought about it,
越X得困惑
the more troubled he became.
如果你想像以光速\
If you imagine traveling at the speed of light,
各方面都充M了矛盾
paradoxes seem to pop up everywhere.
垡蛩固贵@的lF 如此多的
Einstein was shocked to realize that so much
即使是被最ゴ蟮嗤人士
of what had been uncritically accepted as truth
ol件接受的真理
by even the greatest authorities on the subject
竟是大e特e
was just plain wrong.
以高速\r
When traveling at high speeds,
必遵守一些特定的t
there are certain rules which must be obeyed.
垡蛩固狗Q之 相π栽理
Einstein called these rules "The Principles of Relativity."
想像才那位呼[而^
Imagine that young woman who just blew past us
T摩托的年p女士
on the motorbike,
想像她T穿行
imagine she was riding her bike
在宇宙中
through the cosmos.
囊拥奈矬w上l出的光
Light from a moving object travels
不物w是o止是移
at the same speed, no matter whether the object
速度都是一拥
is at rest or in motion.
她的速度K不增加光的速度
Her speed is not added to the speed of light.
乃的摩托l出的光
The light from her motorbike
依然是光的速度
still travels at the speed of light.
大自然的I旨
Nature commands,
汝不可超越光速
"Thou shalt not add my speed to the speed of light."
同 ]有物|
Also, no material object
鞑ニ俣瓤梢赃_到或者超^光速
can travel at or faster than the speed of light.
物理上 ]有什N可以阻止你
There's nothing in physics that prevents you
S心所欲地接近光的速度
from traveling as close to the speed of light as you like.
99.9%的光速 ]}
99.9% of the speed of light is just fine,
但是o你怎N努力
but no matter how hard you try,
都o法得到 最後的那百分c
you never gain that last decimal point.
以F的一致性碚f
For reality to be logically consistent,
必然存在一宇宙速度O限
there must be a cosmic speed limit.
鞭子l出的音是因
The crack of that whip is due to its tip
鞭^的移铀俣瘸^了速
moving faster than the speed of sound.
a生了n舨
It makes a shockwave,
例如@在意大利l村的 一小小的音爆
a mini sonic boom, in the Italian countryside.
打雷也是一拥牡览
A thunderclap works the same way,
有超音速wC掠^r的音
and so does the sound of a passing supersonic jet.
那槭颤N光速
So why is the speed of light
比音速更y超越
any more a barrier than the speed of sound?
答案是 不HH光速
The answer is not just that light travels
比音速快100f倍
about a million times faster than sound.
也因 @不H是一工程W}
And it's not merely an engineering problem,
像建造首架超音速wC那N
like building the first supersonic jet.
光障
Instead, the light barrier
是自然的基本定律
is a fundamental law of nature,
就像f有引力一踊本
as basic as gravity.
垡蛩固檫@世界O定了^Φt
Einstein found his absolute framework for the world,
@o了宇宙\又械
this sturdy pillar among all the relative motions
所有相\有力的支持
within the motions of the cosmos.
光速就是那N快
Light travels just as fast,
o光源移拥目炻
no matter how fast or slow its source is moving.
相ζ渌任何|西 光速是a定的
Speed of light is constant, relative to everything else.
]有什N可以追上光
Nothing can ever catch up with light.
自然定律的ゴ缶褪窃陟
The thing about the laws of nature
他o懈可
is that they're unbreakable.
物理W家的工作就是lF@些定律
The job of physicists is to discover these commandments,
定律不S文化的不同而改
the ones that do not vary from culture to culture
也不Srg而改
or time to time
放之宇宙而皆准
and hold true throughout the cosmos.
@就是楹  如同垡蛩固怪赋龅
That's why, as Einstein showed,
接近光速r就出}了
funny things happen close to the speed of light.
以接近光速的速度旅行
Traveling close to the speed of light
就像是L生不老
is kind of an elixir of life
我的生物慢下
because your biological clock slows down
相於其他人碚f
relative to those you leave behind.
@NF象或S可以槲人
This phenomenon may provide us humans,
只能活1世o左右的人
who only live for a century or so,
提供一可行的a星g旅行的方案
a practical means to travel to the stars,
r空魔法大
where the magic show of spacetime
精彩呈
really gets crazy.
19世o的天文W家 威廉・赫歇
The 19th-century astronomer William Herschel
喜g和他的鹤蛹s翰
loved to share the wonders of the universe
分享宇宙中的奇E
with his son John.
我有朋友 一很明的砘
I once had a friend, very clever fellow,
天文W家 也是Y的牧
an astronomer and a parson at Leeds,
叫 s翰・米切
by the name of John Michell.
你是r 他就^世了
Poor man died when you were a babe,
他安息
God rest his soul.
他孕庞行┬切
He held that some stars
m然看不到
are invisible.
s_存在 但是我永ho法看到
They really exist, but we shall never see them.
米切叫他 「暗星」
"Dark stars," Michell called them.
恕我直言 父H
With all due respect, Father,
你的朋友肯定弄e了
surely your friend was mistaken.
如果]人能看到
If no one can see them,
我怎N能知道它_存在
then how can we possibly know they exist?
你看到留下_印的人了
Did you see the man who left those footprints, John?
] 怎N了
Why, no, Father.
我]看到
I did not.
但你知道他_存在 不是
But do you know that he exists?
s翰 米切是最ゴ蟮目W家之一
John Michell is one of the greatest scientists
你可能]f^
you've probably never heard of.
他生活工作於18世o的英格m
He lived and worked in England in the 18th century.
F在也]有他的像存世
If he ever sat for a portrait, it no longer exists.
有人曾形容他
He was once described by an acquaintance
胖胖的黝黑小矮人
as "a short little man, of black complexion, and fat."
米切O想一巨大的a星
Michell imagined a star so big,
|量巨大到 即使光
so massive, that nothing, not even light,
也o法逃x它的重力吸引
could escape its gravitational grip.
你能找到暗星
Can you find the dark star?
暗星主要由超中性子成 K通^暗物|和正物|的湮玑放能量
你o法用肉眼直接看它
You can't see it with your eyes, not directly,
但在宇宙@沙┥
but it may leave a kind of footprint
它可能留下某N足E
on the cosmic shore.
米切J橐樗巨大的引力
Michell realized that we might be able to detect
使得我或S可以y到他
some of these dark stars because of their extreme gravity.
如果一暗星 碰巧伴S著一
If one happened to be near
稍小些 l光的星星
a smaller, luminous companion star,
那w星星以o密的道
that star would appear to travel in a tight orbit
h@著 看不的|西\行
around nothing.
即使我看不到
Even though we can't see it,
我也知道 有|量超巨大的
we know something with a lot of mass
|西在那Y
has to be right there.
暗星
A dark star,
或者叫 黑洞
or what today we call a black hole.
黑洞L什N幼
What does a black hole look like
它的Y面是什N幼拥
and what would it be like inside?
我以後提到  但是首先
We'll get there, but first,
我先在我的家l稍作休息
let's make a pit stop in my hometown,
~s
New York City,
@地方在我砜
where it's always seemed to me
所有的一切都在不停地\
that everything is in constant motion.
我在@Y住了大半子
I've lived here most of my life.
有新r事物
There's always something new to see.
但有一聿蛔 重力
But one thing never changes-- gravity.
重力在^去的45|年g
Gravity on Earth has been the same
一直保持不
for the past four and a half billion years.
如果 今天 我可以改它
But what if, today, we could alter it?
重力受r空影
Gravity is a distortion
l生畸
in the shape of spacetime
如同垡蛩固固岢龅睦碚
as Einstein showed.
空g可以膨和收s
Space can expand and contract
甚至o限曲
and warp without limit.
如果地球的we和密度
If the Earth's size or density
有微的不同
were even a little different,
它的重力也不同
its gravity would be, too.
有o限的可能性
There's an infinite range of possibilities.
~s人在@Y感受到的
New Yorkers feel right at home
重力挝
in the gravitational pull of the Earth,
我Q 1g
called "one g."
假O我取消一l街上的重力
Suppose we turn off the gravity on one of its streets.
\又械娜撕臀矬w
People and objects that were already in motion
就向上w去
are launched into flight.
如果我把重力加大到
Now what if I turn the gravity up
比方f 8或者9g
to, say, eight or nine g's?
和C起
Out of compassion,
把人拿_
let's evacuate the area.
@重力和痿YCw行T
This is about the same g-force
高速Dr承受的重力相
that a fighter pilot in a high-speed turn would feel.
追昼 不使你受
A few minutes of this wouldn't hurt you,
但是^不舒服
but it wouldn't be comfortable.
在10fgr
At 100,000 g's,
消防栓也被自身的重量
even fire hydrants become crushed
罕饬
by their own enormous weight.
而_到装偃fg
But at millions of g's,
光也被拉
even light bows to gravity.
光依然保持a速
The light still moves at its constant speed,
但它o法逃逸
but it cannot escape.
米切f的暗星
Michell's dark star...
我Q楹诙
our black hole.
最近的一 或S比想像的要近
And the nearest one may be closer than you think.
不是每a星都成黑洞
Not every star can become a black hole.
只有千分之一的|量足虼
Only about one in a thousand is massive enough.
最近的一 可能距x地球不到100光年
The nearest one could be within 100 light years of Earth.
黑洞不是科幻小fY的宇宙吸m器
Black holes aren't the mythic cosmic vacuum cleaners of science fiction.
它不到吞噬
They don't go around gobbling up unsuspecting worlds.
你得去找它
You've got to come to them.
但是如果你去了
But if you do,
可就是有去o回
it might be the last thing you ever see.
才那是我在抵抗上百fg的重力
That was us resisting a few million g's of gravity.
e忘了 那砘锟梢酝淌晒饩
Don't forget, that thing swallows light.
我不能靠的太近
We'll keep our distance.
巨大的a星消耗完它的核燃料
When giant stars exhaust their nuclear fuel,
他不再保持高
they can no longer stay hot enough
以抵消自身向鹊囊力
to fend off the inward pull of their own gravity.
|量最大的a星塌陷
The most massive stars collapse into darkness,
]有光亮 只留下重力
leaving only their gravity behind.
@黑洞⒁超巨星的萎s的企w
This black hole enshrouds the shrunken corpse
[藏其中
of a supergiant star.
a星本身可能萎s到
The star itself has shriveled into something
比黑洞小
even smaller than this darkness,
只有64公里
only 64 kilometers wide.
@是lF的第一黑洞
This is the first black hole ever discovered--
天Z座X-1
Cygnus X-1.
我在地球上是怎NlF
How did we on Earth ever find something
@N小 @N暗 @Nh的 |西
so small and dark and far away?
我通^另一N光 X光
We looked at it in another kind of light. X-rays.
X光中 我看不到In X-ray light, we lost sight of the blue star
因樗的表面囟戎挥形氐3f度
because its surface is a tepid 30,000 degrees.
而黑洞周的怏wAP
But the disk of gas around the black hole
在X光中l出耀眼的光芒 囟雀哌_1|度
glowed brilliantly in X-rays at 100 million degrees.
如同威廉・赫歇所lF的
As William Herschel discovered,
很多a星都有H密的小夥伴  M成星系y
many stars have close companions forming a binary star system.
但如果其中一常巨大
But if one member of such a pair is enormous
另一比^小
and the other is compact,
小的@可以吞噬它兄弟的
the smaller star can drain and consume the atmosphere
大
of its larger sibling.
@N神病PS可以持m装偃f年
This neurotic relationship can last for millions of years.
^大a星的大颖怀榈嵋眼的吸eP上
The atmosphere of the larger star was being siphoned onto
吸eP不停自D
a glowing hot accretion disk that revolves around
K且漩u式的M入黑洞
and spirals into a black hole.
莶豢醯闹亓Σ嗉铀偎The overwhelming gravity was accelerating the blue star's gas
⑵匀胨劳鲣u
into a death spiral,
跨^r空的界限
crossing the spacetime boundary,
一去不头
never to be seen again.
@至P重要的界限⒑诙
The fateful boundary that separates a black hole
c宇宙的其他部分隔x_  被Q 事件界
from the rest of the universe is called an event horizon.
在我看 吸eP中的物|
From our point of view, the substance in the disk
在靠近界r慢下
slows down as it approaches the event horizon,
但^不接|它
never quite reaching it.
如果你站在大怃u上
But if you were riding on that spiraling gas--
我K不建h@N做
and I don't advise it--
酌腌就越^事件界
you would sail past the event horizon in a matter of seconds
M入到 ]人回淼 未知度
into the undiscovered country from which no traveler returns.
我搜索了资星系的中心
We have searched the hearts of dozens of galaxies,
在每Y面都能找到 一|量超大的黑洞
and in every case, we have found a super-massive black hole.
我的y河系也不例外
Our own galaxy is no exception.
最靠近y河系中心的a星\拥乃俣
The stars nearest the center of our galaxy whip around
超^每小r4千f公里
at more than 40 million kilometers an hour.
他怎N\拥倪@N快
What could make them move so fast?
唯一合理的解是
The only logical explanation
y河系中央存在著
is that something with the mass
|量等於4百f太的物w
of four million suns lies at the center.
@4百f太l出的光去哪Y了
So where's the blazing light of four million suns?
既然我看不
Since we can't see it,
它一定是被禁d在黑洞Y了
it must be imprisoned inside a black hole.
地球x得很h 很安全
Earth is far enough away to be perfectly safe.
其他的世界或S]有@N幸\
Other worlds might not be so lucky.
如果你能穿^事件界
If you somehow survived the perilous journey
s活著
across the event horizon,
你可以回^看
you'd be able to look back out
宇宙的整部未硎范
and see the entire future history of the universe
展F在你眼前
unfold before your eyes.
怎N的
How?
因 r空受到
Because when spacetime is warped
黑洞的O度重力影而扭曲
by the extreme gravity of a black hole,
rg被拉伸至O致
time is stretched to the limit.
但你面前是何N景象呢
But what would be in front of you?
我提前警告你
Before we go there, I should warn you
我f的是未涉足^的科WI域
that we're entering uncharted scientific territory.
那Y可能有我未知的物理定律
For all we know, there may be undiscovered laws of physics
支配著黑洞中央的事情
that govern events at the center of a black hole.
在下一垡蛩固钩霈F前
But until the next Einstein comes along,
我碜思想吧
let's perform a thought experiment.
18世o的s翰 米切
That's how John Michell first imagined dark stars
就是靠它想像出 暗星
in the 18th century,
垡蛩固挂彩沁@N想出他的...
and how Einstein conceived of his theory of rela...
父H 你相信有鬼魂
Father, do you believe in ghosts?
我不信有 人的鬼魂
Oh, no, not in the human kind of ghosts.
完全不信
No, not at all.
但是 向上看 鹤
But look up, my boy,
M天都是鬼魂
and see a sky full of them.
你如果去^黑洞能活著回
If you could survive the trip into a black hole,
你可能lF
you might emerge in another place
我宇宙中的其他rg和空g
and time in our own universe,
先不提 相φ的第一l戒律
circumventing the first commandment of relativity...
汝不可超越光速
thou shalt not travel faster than light.
太空中]有什N速度可以比光速快
Nothing can move through space faster than light.
但太空K不空
But space is not mere emptiness.
空g可以延伸 收s  被扭曲
Its properties can stretch and shrink and can be deformed.
那拥脑 rg也被扭曲
And when that happens, time is deformed, too.
垡蛩固拱lF 空g和rg 只是
Einstein discovered that spaceand time are just two aspects
一事物的方面  r空
of the same thing, spacetime.
r空本身可以被任意曲
Spacetime itself can deform enough
用任意速度你去任意地方
to carry you anywhere at any speed.
黑洞可能是不同宇宙g的隧道
Black holes may very well be tunnels through the universe.
通^@N星Hg的交通系y 你可以
On this intergalactic subway system, you could travel
_到r空的最h端
to the farthest reaches of spacetime,
或S其他更@人的地方
or you might arrive in someplace even more amazing.
或S是完全不一拥挠钪
We might find ourselves in an altogether different universe.
但是一黑洞怎N能容But how can a whole universe fit inside of a black hole,
黑洞只是我宇宙中的很小一部分
which is only a small part of our universe?
@又是一r空出的蚍
It's another magic trick of spacetime.
黑洞oc比的引力
The phenomenal gravity of a black hole
可以⒄宇宙的空g扭曲K塞M去
can warp the space of an entire universe inside it.
我F在受到的引力 或S很
Our local gravity might be a drag to us,
但so法和
but it's really feeble compared
萎sa星炔康囊力 相提K
with what goes on inside a collapsed star.
我所知
As far as we know,
超大a星萎s成黑洞r
when a giant star collapses to make a black hole,
中心a生O大的密度和毫
the extreme density and pressure at the center
如同Q生宇宙的大爆炸
mimic the Big Bang, which gave rise to our universe.
於是黑洞日Q生了一宇宙
And a universe inside a black hole
@宇宙可能a生它自己的黑洞
might give rise to its own black holes.
@些黑洞 又a生其他的宇宙
And those could lead to other universes.
或S我的宇宙就是如此
Maybe that's how our cosmos came to be.
所周知
For all we know,
如果你想知道黑洞Y面有什N
if you want to see what it's like inside a black hole,
只要看看四周
just look around you.
威廉・赫歇lF了 太
William Herschel went on to discover that the sun
е它的行星 在y河系中\行
and its planets are moving through the Milky Way.
他的鹤佑惺颤N成就呢
And whatever became of his son John?
他成榱艘晃ゴ蟮目W家
He grew up to become a great scientist.
在他父H的基A上 他所得出的外太空^yY果
His deep-space observations built on those of his father
成榱诵窍誓夸的依
to become the basis for the standard catalog of galaxies
沿用至今
we use today.
威廉身w不好r  s翰陪著他
When William was in failing health, John stayed with him
在望hR旁 度^L夜
through the long nights at his telescope
退^ya星
to help him sweep the stars.
父H^世後 s翰下墓I
And when his father died, John wrote his epitaph...
他推倒天堂的
"He broke through the walls of heaven."
s翰常
John often reminisced
c他父H度^的那些夏日夜晚
about those summer nights with his father.
@或S就是楹 他要ふ冶４孢^去的方法
Maybe that's why he sought a way to preserve the past.
s翰 赫歇 是一N展F形式的rg旅行的
John Herschel was one of the founders
始人之一
of a new form of time travel,
一N保留光和的k法
a means to capture light and memories.
他樗x窳艘名字
He actually coined a word for it,
z影
photography.
你@N想
When you think about it,
z影是rg旅行的一N形式
photography is a form of time travel.
装倌昵暗娜俗⒁著我
This man is staring at us from across the centuries...
光勾勒出的鬼魂
a ghost preserved by light.
不y想像 在不h的未
It's not hard to imagine that in the near future,
我可以保留^去
we'll be able to capture the past
以三S立w的形式
in all three dimensions.
我可以走M一段
We'll be able to step inside a memory.
或S不能回到^去的rg
It may not be possible to travel backward in time,
但可能 有一天 可以⑦^去憩F在
but perhaps, one day, we can bring the past to us.
@是我^去的一刻
Here's a moment from my past.
就像s翰赫歇
Like John Herschel,
我得幼年的我
I'm remembering a younger version of myself.
1975年12月20
December 20, 1975.
~s的一雪天
A snowy day in Ithaca, New York.
生命旅程的一拐c
A branchpoint on the road that brought me
我有C站在@Y
to this moment with you.
那天我遇到了卡・塞根
It was the day I met Carl Sagan.
就如同天空中那些星星的鬼魂
Reminds me of those ghost stars in the sky...
即使已消亡 但星光依然照耀我
you know, the ones that still shine their light upon us long after they're gone.